Guide to the Coudert, Frederic R., Sr. Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Coudert, Frederic R., Sr. Papers
1863-1962.
Coudert, Frederic R. (Frederic René), 1871-1955.
9 linear feet (19 document boxes).
Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY 10027.
MS#0289
4078446
This collection contains correspondence, subjects files and scrapbooks pertaining to Frederick R. Coudert, Sr.
Biographical Note
Frederic René Coudert (Columbia A.B., 1890; A.M., 1891; Ph.D., 1894) admitted to the New York Bar, 1892. Special assistant Attorney General of U.S., 1915-20; legal advisor to the British Embassy, 1915-20; Trustee of Columbia University, 1912-54. Author of "Certainty and Justice," 1913.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, subject files, and scrapbooks concerning Coudert's law practice, political activities, social life and family. The cataloged and arranged correspondence covers the period 1935 through 1938 and deals with law and international affairs. Among th cataloged correspondence are: Harry Armstrong, Boris Bakhmeteff, Nicholas Murray Butler, Benjamin N. Cardozo, Learned Hand, Cordell Hull, Philip C. Jessup, Walter Lipmann, Robert McElroy, and Hendrik W. Van Loon. The subject files document Coudert's involvemant with the American, New York City, and New York State Bar Associations and the 1936-38 International Olympic Committee. The subject files on Columbia University cover the years 1933-37 and include, in addition to general correspondence concerning Coudert's activities as a Trustee of the University, correspondence on the Trustees' Committe on Honors and the Committee on Legal Affairs. The 21 scrapbooks contain clippings on all aspects of Coudert's political, professional, and personal life from 1888 to 1931.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in four series:
Series I: Cataloged correspondence (Box 1)
Series II: Arranged correspondence (Boxes 1-4)
Series III: Correspondence by subject (Boxes 5-8)
Series IV: Scrapbooks: (21 v. Boxes 10-19)
Subjects
Columbia University.; International Olympic Committee.; American Bar Association.; New York State Bar Association.; Association of the Bar of the City of New York.; Bakhmeteff, Boris Aleksandrovich, 1880-1951.; Armstrong, Harry.; Cardozo, Benjamin N. (Benjamin Nathan), 1870-1938.; Hand, Learned, 1872-1961.; Jessup, Philip C. (Philip Caryl), 1897-1986.; Scrapbooks; Lawyers.
Acquisition
09/28/87 M-87-09-28 Coudert, Paula M. Gift
Bequest of Paula M. Coudert, 1987.
Access Restrictions
The following boxes are located off-site: Boxes 2-19. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
- Series I: Catalogued Correspondence
  - Adams, James Truslow (Box 1)
  - Armstrong, Harry (Box 1)
  - Bakhmeteff, Boris Aleksandrovich (Box 1)
  - Baldensperger, Fernand (Box 1)
  - Barry, Herbert T. (Box 1)
  - Bergson, Henri (Box 1)
  - Bingham, Robert W. (Box 1)
  - Butler, Nicholas Murray (Box 1)
  - Campbell, Gerald (Box 1)
  - Cardozo, Benjamin N. (Box 1)
  - Chamberlain, Austen (Box 1)
  - Connally, Tom (Box 1)
  - Cortissoz, Royal (Box 1)
  - Coykendall, Frederick (Box 1)
  - Crane, Frederick E. (Box 1)
  - Easley, Ralph M. (Box 1)
  - Gildersleeve, Virginia Crocheron (Box 1)
  - Graves, Frank Pierrepont (Box 1)
  - Hand, Learned (Box 1)
  - Haskell, Henry S. (Box 1)
  - Hayes, Cardinal Patrick J. (Box 1)
  - Hazard, Paul (Box 1)
  - Houston, Herbert S. (Box 1)
  - Hughes, Charles E. (Box 1)
  - Hull, Cordell (Box 1)
  - Hyde, James H. (Box 1)
  - Jessup, Philip C. (Box 1)
  - King, Willard (Box 1)
  - La Guardia, Fiorello H. (Box 1)
  - Lippmann, Walter (Box 1)
  - McElroy, Robert (Box 1)
  - Shotwell, James T. (Box 1)
  - Stimson, Henry L. (Box 1)
  - Tweed, Harrison (Box 1)
  - Van Loon, Hendrik Willem (Box 1)
  - Wagner, Robert (Box 1)
  - Wardwell, Allen (Box 1)
- Series II: Arranged Correspondence
  - 1925-1936 A-Z (Box 2)
  - 1937-1938 A-G (Box 3)
  - L-O (Box 4)
  - P-Z (Box 5)
- Series III: Correspondence by Subject
  - American Bar Association (Box 6)
  - Bellinger, J.B. (Box 6)
  - Clifford, Rev. C. (Box 6)
  - Columbia University
    - Committee on Honors (Box 6)
    - Committee on Legal Affairs (Box 6)
    - General File (Box 6)
  - Coudert, F.W. (Box 7)
  - Coudert, T. (Box 7)
  - Flanders Club (Box 7)
  - Garrison (Box 7)
  - International Olympic Committee (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
  - New York City Bar Association (Box 7)
  - New York State Bar Association (Box 7)
  - Condolence Letters on the Death of F.R. Coudert (Box 8)
  - Condolence Letters on the death of Mrs. F.R. Coudert (Box 9)
  - Clippings (Box 9)
- Series IV: Scrapbooks: political, professional and personal clippings
  - Scrapbook 1, 1888-1891 (Box 10)
  - Scrapbook 2, 1893 (Box 10)
  - Scrapbook 3, 1894 (Box 10)
  - Scrapbook 4, 1894-1896 (Box 11)
  - Scrapbook 5, 1895-1896 (Box 11)
  - Scrapbook 6, 1896-1897 (Box 11)
  - Scrapbook 7, 1910-1911 (Box 12)
  - Scrapbook 8, 1910-1911 (Box 13)
  - Scrapbook 9, 1911-1912 (Box 13)
  - Scrapbook 10, 1912-1913 (Box 14)
  - Scrapbook 11, 1913 (Box 14)
  - Scrapbook 12, 1913-1914 (Box 15)
  - Scrapbook 13, 1917 (Box 15)
  - Scrapbook 14, 1917-1918 (Box 16)
  - Scrapbook 15, 1918-1919 (Box 16)
  - Scrapbook 16, 1918-1919 (Box 17)
  - Scrapbook 17, 1919 (Box 17)
  - Scrapbook 18, 1921-1922 (Box 18)
  - Scrapbook 19, 1929 (Box 18)
  - Scrapbook 20, 1929-1930 (Box 19)
  - Scrapbook 21, 1930-1931 (Box 19)